# Hao Jiang, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Fellow Harvard John A. Paulson School Of Engineering And Applied Sciences 150 Western Ave, Boston, MA 02134

(315)267-6271 hajiang@seas.harvard.edu https://harperjiang.github.io

I am an accomplished Postdoctoral Researcher at Harvard University. My research involves self-designing blockchain and large language models. They have many potential applications in a variety of industries. Previously, I earned my Ph.D. in Computer Science from the University of Chicago, where I specialized in Databases, Distributed Systems, and Machine Learning. I have authored several publications in leading academic conferences. With six years of experience as a Software Engineer, I am well-versed in Java, C++, and Python. I also have experience leading small teams.

## Research and Work Experience

## Harvard University

Boston, MA

Postdoctoral Researcher with Prof. Stratos Idreos

 $Oct\ 2021\ -\ Now$ 

- Build a self-designing blockchain system that adapts to workloads to provide high-throughput and low-latency
- Develop a small and detachable memory component for large language models. These
  components maintain domain knowledge and long-term memory and can be trained
  independently from the main LLM. They grant the LLM different abilities with low cost.

Facebook Inc.

Menlo Park, CA

Software Engineer Intern

 $July.\ 2018-Sept.\ 2018$ 

- Design, implement and evaluate a load balance algorithm for PHP requests

### The University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

Research Assistant under Prof. Aaron J. Elmore

Sept. 2015 - Aug. 2021

- Develop a Compression-Aware Query Engine for Columnar Database that has 5x performance compared to the state-of-the-art. Result published on SIGMOD.
- Design a neural network based classifier to choose the best compression algorithm for a given dataset.
- Develop an innovative, fast, and efficient compression algorithm for String data. The algorithm compresses better and faster than the previous state-of-the-art. Result published on VLDB.
- Develop a fast query algorithm on compressed data without decompression. It queries compressed data 20-100x faster.
- Use auto-encoder architecture for data compression in approximate data queries.

## Clarkson University

Potsdam, NY

Research Assistant under Prof. Jeanna N. Matthews

Sept. 2012 - Jul. 2015

 Build an Internet Topology Platform. The platform simulates the latency of two arbitrary Internet nodes to facilitate easy Internet structure analysis.

Baidu Inc. Shanghai, China

System Architect

Sept. 2011 - Aug. 2012

Design and implement a customizable MySQL replication framework. This framework listens
to MySQL master-slave replication messages, and rewrite the message with user-provided
functions. It allows easy customization of replication behaviors.

BigData Analysis on Hadoop. Led a 4-developer team to design and develop a Hadoop-based
 BigData analysis system. The system processes a daily data volume of over 10 terabytes.

### OOCL Co. Ltd.

Shanghai, China

Senior Software Engineer

Sept. 2005 - Sept. 2011

- Production Server JVM Performance Tuning. Design and implement a log analysis system for production environment JVM resource leak and memory leak tracing and tuning.
- Design and optimization of an accounting system containing billions of rows and processing millions of queries hourly based on Oracle DBMS.

## **Skills**

- Computer Science: Database, Distributed Systems, Parallel Programming, Machine Learning
- Tech Stack: Java, Scala, C/C++, Python, Golang, Matlab, Javascript, HTML/CSS
- **Teamworking:** Experience of leading small development teams

#### **Education**

The University of Chicago

Chicago, IL

Ph.D. Computer Science

2015 - 2021

- Advisor: Aaron J. Elmore

Clarkson University

Potsdam, NY

M.Sc. Computer Science

2012 - 2015

- Advisors: Jeanna N. Matthews

Fudan University

Shanghai, China

B.Sc. Computer Science

2001 - 2005

## **Publications**

- 1. Chunwei Liu, **Hao Jiang**, John Paparrizos, Aaron J. Elmore Decomposed Bounded Floats for Fast Compression and Queries VLDB 2021
- 2. **Hao Jiang**, Chunwei Liu, John Paparrizos, Andrew A. Chien, Jihong Ma, Aaron J. Elmore, *Good to the last bit: Data-Driven Encoding with CodecDB*, SIGMOD 2021
- 3. **Hao Jiang**, Chunwei Liu, Qi Jin, John Paparrizos, Aaron J. Elmore, *PIDS: Attribute Decomposition for Improved Compression and Query Performance in Columnar Storage*, *VLDB* 2020
- Chunwei Liu, McKade Umbenhower, Hao Jiang, Aaron J. Elmore, Mostly Order Preserving Dictionaries, ICDE 2019
- 5. **Hao Jiang**, Aaron J. Elmore, Boosting Data Filtering on Columnar Encoding with SIMD, DaMon 2018

- 6. Dixin Tang, **Hao Jiang**, Aaron J. Elmore, Adaptive Concurrency Control: Despite the Looking Glass, One Concurrency Control Does Not Fit All, CIDR 2017
- 7. **Hao Jiang**, Yaoqing Liu, Jeanna N. Matthews, *IP Geolocation Estimation using Neural Networks with Stable Landmarks*, *IEEE INFOCOM Workshop GI 2016*
- 8. Wenjin Hu, Long Zhang, **Hao Jiang**, Jeanna N. Matthews, A Quantitative Study of Virtual Machine Live Migration, CAC 2013